visually from our point of view it will
seem like goor rock is the title sponsor
but they are not the title sponsor they
always have cool demos they do stuff
like late at night under the lights for
the audience it's fun you're right there
on the waterfront there's a Cool vibe to
it that I keep thinking that there's a
cap and they just doesn't seem to be a
cap and because of that he becomes very
exciting to watch he looks like he's at
some point going to reach the cap and
then he just never does it is 2024 maybe
the strongest year in human history at
least if we have something to say about
it and we are back with strength weekly
the first brand new episode bringing you
news from around the barbell game I am
one of your hosts David Thomas to I am
joined by the Intrepid the incomparable
the very kind Phil Blackman let's get to
today's run of show we got four big
stories coming to you live it's not live
we actually record this ahead of time
the first is we start to answer how
strong are crossfitters exactly because
two-time CrossFit Games ch Champion
Justin mados entered a powerlifting
competition totaled over 1,400 lb
segment number two Go Ruck is named the
official apparel and Footwear partner of
CrossFit and becomes the biggest partner
for the new CrossFit Game season but is
not a title sponsor meaning there will
be no title sponsor for the 2024
CrossFit Games we break that down well
this one is actually from 2023 the best
weightlifters of 2023 we highlight a few
of those and finally water paloa the
first big competition of the year's
calendar is kicking off this weekend we
bring you a little preview because
right so we're bringing you all the
goodness there Phil how are you feeling
in 2024 and are you recovered from the
holidays I don't know if there's any
amount of time in 2024 to recover from
the holidays and the Damage that I did
to my body but we're g to give it a go
we're gonna give it a go David well I
put on some kilograms of mass over the
holidays I wouldn't call it lean mass
but you know what that's for you to
judge and for me me to find out all
right Phil let's dive into it this one
happened a few weeks ago but a lot of
folks missed it for the holidays justtin
madero's a two-time CrossFit Games
champion and he of the best mullet in
sports there I said it the best mullet
in all sports not just string Sports
into a powerlifting competition and did
pretty darn well as a 90 kilo lifter
Phil how did Justin do so Justin
competed in the 90 kilogram class like
you said at 2023 usapl holiday hoist
which is a fun name that was right
before the holidays on December 16th and
he went eight for n in his first
performance he got a silver medal
overall he hit 232 a half kilograms or
512 a half pounds in his squat pretty
big squat he's uh bench pressed 137 a
half kilograms that's breaking the 300
pound barrier and he deadlifted 272 and
a half kilograms that is also breaking
the 600 pound Mark so it's clear that he
had these goals in mind it seems like
because his final lifts were breaking
these particular milestones we've seen a
trajectory from Justin that he's gotten
stronger and stronger over the last
couple of years in his early time in
CrossFit at the elite at the elite level
it was clear that his weak point was the
barbell game he was falling behind guys
like Adler and velner like those guys
are just really really powerful with
barbells in their hands and we've seen
him get much much much stronger in that
and this performance here where he's
focused entirely on strength really
shows how far he's come and where we can
expect him to go come the 2024 season
kicking off with the open in February I
think that MOS has definitely upped his
strength we since we saw him come on the
scene as a relatively young competitor
but he's still not I'd call you know one
of the five strongest uh individual
CrossFit Games competitors there are
many names I would put above him as far
as limit strength now he's a two-time
champ let's just note he's he's great at
what he does but I still wouldn't say
that his limit strength is in that very
very very top tier so the fact that he's
hitting these numbers indicates you know
the base level of strength for the for
the top cross games competitors has
definitely gone up we've seen that in
Olympic lifting as well we talked about
that a few episodes ago it's kind it's
kind of cool to see that in powerlifting
because like they got to lift a standard
they got to hit depth on the squat you
know they can't hitch on the deadlift
it's good to see competition standards
actually be upheld and see how crossers
do in that environment let's keep it in
CrossFit that was kind of a weird meld
of powerlifting and Crossfit let's go
specifically back to CrossFit goor Rock
has stepped in and is now the biggest
sponsor or the I guess headlining you
could call it sponsor
of the CrossFit games but there is not
like a branded CrossFit games anymore
Phil did this one surprise you it did in
that there's a lot of nuance to it so
Goro has named the official apparel and
Footwear partner that's what they are
officially but in terms of what we're
told to expect of how it's going to look
at the actual games themselves visually
from our point of view it will seem like
goor rock is the title sponsor but they
are not the title sponsor so it's not
the go rock CrossFit Games it's cross
games but they are they're going to have
the biggest presence there especially if
you're on the ground during the games
for all intents and purposes on on our
side and from a spectator's point of
view side we would we should be looking
at goor Ruck as the new Noble in that
sense but they are not the official
title sponsor if that means anything for
people out there and goor Ruck is is
known for their their their bags their
their Ruck sacks right that's what
they're best known for that was kind of
their first product line but they're now
the apparel and Footwear line they're
actually going to be launching it seems
like a new line of CrossFit focused
Footwear you know I I do think that this
is smart for goor Ruck to kind of
broaden their appeal and like show folks
hey we have other products because in my
mind Ruck sacks goruck ruck sack so it's
an interesting move you know locking up
the Footwear and apparel that's always
been the biggest sponsor of the Cross to
games ever since the rebok days right
ever since that 10-year contract with
Reebok what's interesting to me is that
if you go back in time if you dial back
the clock eight or nine years ago a lot
of folks thought that the successor to
that was going to be Nike I kind of
thought that Nike was gonna come in I
speculated that Nike was gonna come in
and take the title sponsorship and I
really thought that when they signed
Matt Fraser probably eight years ago he
was the hot Athlete on the scene they
released the Nike metcon right which was
going specifically it seemed like seemed
like toward the crowd that the rebok
Nano was marketed to and it didn't pan
out CrossFit changed ownership
uh the pandemic hit like it just seemed
like these Mega established public
company brands moved away from wanting
to sponsor become the title sponsor for
the CrossFit game so definitely a
different series of developments than I
anticipated but again that's just my
personal speculation we both were on on
lined on Matt Frasier being where the
where it was going to lean towards
because he was the successor to to Fring
but when he came out saying that between
workouts he would crush Snickers bars
and then lie to his opponent to his
competitors and say that they were like
oh no no the protein bars the protein
bars but he was like I just need the
calories I need I need the carbs to like
get through these workouts and do it
effectively bro if I if that happened
and Snickers didn't become the the title
sponsor if it wasn't the Snickers
CrossFit game I mean my head was like
Snickers is gonna sponsor this thing I
mean if you go far back in the archives
some of the early Crosser games I forget
which year so don't don't hold a candle
to my feet on this but I forget which
year it was like 2008 maybe Panda
Express was an early sponsor of the
early CrossFit games when they were at
uh the ranch at Castro's family ranch so
awesome
so you know thing and then Monster
Energy monster that was last year yeah
they I mean 2021 that was the first like
post pandemic when I was there monster
had a whole tent set up they had a whole
tent and people were like getting aggro
about it people were like oh I can't
believe monster it's like you know they
it's like sugar and and stuff and it's
not good and it's like dude Frasier was
touting that he was crushing Snickers
mid games I just want to be clear
neither monster nor Snickers are
sponsoring this show if you'd like to if
either of those Brands would like to
sponsor the show our our DMS are very
open I I will crush I will casually
Crush so many Snickers on this cast
strength weekly brought to you by
Snickers I do feel M peckish after these
recording so I can use yeah okay okay
favorite candy bar Phil favorite candy
bar it's it's Snickers it's it is it's
legitimately actually Snickers have you
ever had the Snickers ice cream bars yes
next level they are like dude like if
you if you want like a nice transition
to that just put your Snickers in the
fridge just eat your actual Snickers
bars
cold but but the Snickers ice cream bars
are they hit different from me oh peanut
butter ice cream because it's peanut
butter ice cream David good oh my again
we don't have no stickers are not
sponsoring this but hey shout out like
we we are very avable our bodies are
ready let's move to another sport where
I have seen athletes crush candy bars uh
in the warm-up area and that's
weightlifting because Barb Ben's own
Jake Dixon Jake Dixon's awesome and he
is a one of the smartest folks in the
weightlifting space he wrote an article
about the 10 top weightlifters of 2023
which is important because 2024 is an
Olympic year we got the Paris olymp OIC
games coming up this summer
weightlifting is a sport I mean by the
skin of its teeth honestly weightlifting
is a sport it was not kicked out of the
Olympic program it will be a sport here
and it will be a sport in 2028 please
read that article at the link in the
description below that's actually going
to be really important because I mean I
think it's one of the best weightlifting
articles to be published in quite some
time a lot of overlooked performances of
that list Phil before we get into these
four that we're going to highlight who
was your favorite to watch in 2023 of
the 10 names
that Jake Dixon put on that list I feel
like after watching Hampton Morris over
the last handful of years it just seems
like the dude doesn't have a limit like
I keep thinking like at some point he'll
like reach his threshold and be like
okay this is where he stands at the
World level and then he just keeps
breaking it now I get it he's still a
teenager he has a lot of room to grow
but at the same time he's been doing it
since he was 16 that I keep thinking
that there's a cap and there just
doesn't seem to be a cap and because of
that he becomes very exciting to watch
because he looks he looks like he's at
some point going to reach the cap and
then he just never does and it's
fantastic 19 years old I'm going to read
his kind of tale of the tape for 2023 he
got second at a grand iwf Grand Prix he
got first at the Pan-American
championships he bummed out of the world
weightlifting championships but hold
that thought because there's a little
bit of a of a catch there he got second
at the junior World Championships he got
fifth at another iwf grand prix let's
talk about the World Championships where
he bombed out did not make a snatch in
the men 61 kilo a group
but he won the cleaning Jerks with 168
kilogram
lift which beat the reigning Olympic
champion Lee fabine of China no American
male had won a gold medal at the senior
World Championships in 51 years
19-year-old Hampton Morris breaking that
streak so it was like a shining Ray of
sunlight after a bomb out and shows it
like oh he can go Toad on the cleaning
jks oh he can go he can you want to go
you want to go let's take this out back
in clean iner hampon Morris pretty
awesome accomplishment there the fact
that on the World level he is at high
end of the cleaning jerk and he's not
even 20 years old yet I know we've
talked about young lifters before but
like dude when I was 18 I could barely
Crush two stickers in a row and this
dude this dude this dude is breaking
cleaning jerk World Records so dude that
is he put so many Snickers overhead dude
how many Snickers is 168 kilograms like
it's so many it's so many Snickers it's
got to be thousands of Snickers it's got
to be I It's gotta be it's Gotta Be how
many Snickers per kilogram we got to do
that conversion we'll get a scale all
right the next one person person we want
to highlight isn't a person it's a whole
team team North Korea had a four-year
Hiatus Co related doping related like
there's there's a lot of reasons that we
haven't seen team North Korea for a
while but they came back to
International competition at the Asian
games they won more medals than any
other country and their women set five
count of five world records and an iwf
Grand Prix the second one of the year
and you're looking at this team like oh
my God this is the best weightlifting
team in the world or could be among the
best weightlifting teams in the world
their athletes are going to kill it and
sweep up in Paris uh but guess what
they're not going to sweep up in Paris
because they didn't qualify as a team
for Paris and there are again reasons
for that are they compliant with doping
controls y y y there's a lot there uh
but you know they're basically going to
have the best weightlifting team in the
world that we're not going to see at the
Paris Olympics which is interesting I
don't think that there's any doubt that
we're going to see China continue its
dominance in 2024 I doubt that that will
fade even remotely at all come 2028 so I
mean we do have to wait but like it's
kind of like everybody's really only
vying for the silver so if like a new
team can actually train and get to the
point where they could maybe contend
with China that would be probably
actually definitely very exciting for
the sport well North Korea could could
not only contend but at the Olympic
level they don't give out team medals
like they they they've shown especially
on the women's side they can contend and
beat and like beat China right in some
of these categories so pretty darn
interesting the last thing we want to
highlight is Ramat Irwin Abdullah of
Indonesia who I think is maybe
pound-for-pound the most exciting lifter
to watch because this is a lifter who
not only dominates and does well ACR
he's actually bounced between weight
classes he's competed as both a 73 and
an undersized 81 in 2023 and did well in
both categories at the international
level but his Showmanship I think is
unparalleled in today's weightlifting
world he flexes like dude hits his last
lift and gets on stage he's doing like
front double biceps he's doing like side
chest and biceps poses he's like
treating that like a like a pose down
after his final clean a j
and I'm sure it annoys some officials
but as a weightlifting spectator I love
to see it dude showing off the guns like
bringing the gun show after his list and
clearly having fun with it he is a metal
contender in Paris in my mind like very
much a metal Contender and just super
exciting to watch you know like I just
love every time he's on stage especially
after his final lifts if he makes them
I'm expecting some fireworks and he's
being a metal contender in what I would
argue is the two most difficult category
for the men yeah the the 73s and the 81s
are I mean both are stacked down the
entire a group so Shey young who's been
dominant I mean I I I cover him
constantly because he has been dominant
at 73 but like being able to compete at
73 and P and be in Podium contention
that alone makes you exciting and then
the fact that this guy's got Showmanship
on top of that makes it even more so
let's get to our fourth and final news
story to kick off the new year because
the first major competition in the
strength sports calendar is wooa in
Miami Miami welcome to Miami WAP
palooza is for the CrossFit Community
there have been times when it is
officially tied to CrossFit there have
been times when it's not officially tied
to CrossFit but let's be honest this is
where the first competition of the Year
where we see the top CrossFit athletes
show up and throw down as both
individuals and teams it's also one of
the more exciting team events in the
calendar because we see a lot of people
who will compete individually during the
year during the regular cross Game
season they'll actually compete on teams
in wooa wapo is known for always having
swim events you're right there on the
waterfront in Miami it's gorgeous it's
fun um I went to woa for the first time
in 2014 I think it was either 2013 or
2014 it's a it's a hoot and a holler it
is a riot down there and uh you want to
have a good time in Miami in January uh
W ploa right on the waterfront is a a
place to uh be and Phil right before we
start recording today they released the
rosters correct what stood out to you as
far as the rosters they sure did so
competing on the men's side uh in as an
individual we're gonna get to see G
malos return to competition uh he was
absent at the games he didn't qualify he
missed done in the semi-finals but he is
always a blast to watch and he'll be
back he's representing Brazil obviously
we're gonna see Roman kov he's still
competing as an individual he'll be here
Sam Quant is going to be back Spencer
panck a bunch of big names that do
compete as individuals on the elite side
will still be there Colton Mertens he
usually does what w paloa Alexander
Corone all the names that you would
expect they will they will be here if
they're not on there they're likely
competing on teams on the women's side
uh some standouts you have Caroline
Stanley she'll be here you have Emily de
Roy she'll be back Emily rol will be
back Emma Carey she's competing as an
individual uh Gabriela mgala she's
competing as an individual so there is a
lot of action to be had and if you
actually get a chance to either watch it
uh live streamed or actually be present
one of the most fun events to watch at w
paloa is the chipper that they always do
on the water and it is a blast to watch
a because chippers are exciting but B
the the aesthetic around that event is
just it's very very cool for the first
time in 2024 there's going to be a
second W paloa later in September there
is W paloa SoCal they're going to
California and they're gonna have a w
paloa event in Huntington Beach so
that's scheduled for September 20 20th
through the 22nd as exciting as Miami
will be you'll get a second dose of it
for the first time in 2024 so there you
go it's it's pretty exciting and I will
say the energy at water is unique in
this space they always have cool demos
they do stuff like late at night under
the lights for the audience you know
you'll have they've done like
weightlifting demos powerlifting demos
it's it's fun you're right there on the
waterfront there's a Cool vibe to it
look the September one post CrossFit
Game season if I were some CrossFit
Games athletes like even if I weren't
wanting to compete and I wanted to like
take you know a couple months off or
just to like chill I just go there as a
spectator and have a ton of fun right
like you eat well if you want to embibe
it's the option you're in Miami or even
SoCal I'm not as familiar with huntingon
Beach um good times for for for
scheduling purposes what that what that
would look like it will be post CrossFit
games but pre- Rogue Invitational it is
interesting it is interesting like back
to back to back there's like a triplet
of these big competitions to kind of
like end the summer head into fall that
is all we got today folks we'll be back
next week with even more strength weekly
I'm David Thomas to uh who are you who
have I been talking to for the past
whatever minutes uh I'm Phil bman ready
to get sponsored by Snickers we had a
blast talking to you about strength on
strength weekly this week thanks
everybody for joining go over to barbend
read all the articles that we talked
about everything is great 2024 is going
to be awesome woohoo leap
[Music]
gear